<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-26T11:42:30+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Theo Knights</title><subtitle>I am a PhD student in the Department of Near Eastern Languages and Civilizations at the University of Chicago, where I study the early modern Ottoman Empire. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">MEHAT Call for Papers — 2023-24</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/08/25/mehat-call.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MEHAT Call for Papers — 2023-24" /><published>2023-08-25T00:10:23+03:00</published><updated>2023-08-25T00:10:23+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/08/25/mehat-call</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/08/25/mehat-call.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Middle East History and Theory Workshop (MEHAT) is now accepting submissions for Fall quarter 2023 and beyond. We invite submissions from graduate students, postdocs, and faculty to present their research (in progress or completed) on the Islamicate world, or to lead directed readings of recently published academic literature offering new approaches to the study of the Islamicate world.</p>

<p>We are eager to hear from historians, linguists, anthropologists, literary scholars, sociologists, musicologists, scholars of religion, and political scientists whose work engages with a broad geography, including but not limited to, the Mediterranean, North and West Africa, and South and Central Asia, from Late Antiquity and the advent of Islam to the present. Within this context, MEHAT is also particularly eager to promote wide-ranging discussions on general points of historical inquiry, theory, and method. NELC faculty members Hakan Karateke and Ghenwa Hayek advise the workshop.</p>

<p>MEHAT typically meets weekly on Thursdays during the term. More details on meeting time and location, as well as a provisional schedule, will be released at the start of the Fall quarter.</p>

<p>We encourage proposals from both regular attendees and from those new to the workshop. If you would like to present your work or a guided reading for discussion and feedback this fall, please submit a brief proposal and provisional title to Theo (knightst[at]uchicago[dot]edu) by September 23rd.</p>

<p>Best wishes,
<br />Theo Knights &amp; Darragh Winkelman</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MEHAT" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Middle East History and Theory Workshop (MEHAT) is now accepting submissions for Fall quarter 2023 and beyond. We invite submissions from graduate students, postdocs, and faculty to present their research (in progress or completed) on the Islamicate world, or to lead directed readings of recently published academic literature offering new approaches to the study of the Islamicate world.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MEHAT Schedule — 2022-23</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/07/21/mehat-schedule.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MEHAT Schedule — 2022-23" /><published>2023-07-21T00:10:23+03:00</published><updated>2023-07-21T00:10:23+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/07/21/mehat-schedule</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mehat/2023/07/21/mehat-schedule.html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you to all participants and presenters for an excellent year of MEHAT gatherings. Here is a brief overview of our events during the past year:</p>

<h4>Winter 2023:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>1/5 – Student coordinator led discussion of A Culture of Ambiguity: An Alternative History of Islam by Thomas Bauer</li>
  <li>1/13 – Burning Books in Ottoman Lands w/ Prof. Hakan Karateke (UChicago NELC)</li>
  <li>1/20 – An Analysis of Ottoman Poetry w/ Darragh Winkelman (UChicago Linguistics)</li>
  <li>1/27 – MEHAT Lunchtime Chat w/ Prof. Dana Sajdi (Boston College)</li>
  <li>2/10 – The Complicated History of the Turkic Word Qımız w/ Dr. Helga Anetshofer (UChicago NELC)</li>
  <li>3/3 – The Aramaic Origin of a Syntactic Construction in Levantine and Iraqi Arabic w/ Sami Jiries (UChicago NELC &amp; Linguistics)</li>
</ul>
<p><b></b></p>
<h4>Spring 2023:</h4>
<ul>
<li>3/27 – MEHAT Coffee w/ Prof. Judith Pfeiffer (University of Bonn) and Prof. Evrim Binbaş (University of Bonn)</li>
<li>3/30 – Empires of the Steppe: Russian, Ottoman, Persian and Chinese Empires in Comparative Perspective w/ Prof. Michael Khodarkovsky (Loyola University Chicago History)</li>
<li>4/06 – The Role of Word-Level Stress in the Khutbas of Ali Ibn Abi Talib w/ Darragh Winkelman (UChicago Linguistics)</li>
<li>4/13 – The Origins of an Ottoman Bourgeois Social Reformer: Recontextualizing Mustafa Suphi’s Early Thought w/ Theo Knights (UChicago NELC)</li>
<li>4/20 – Reconstructing Early Islamic Texts Through Excavating Later Texts w/ Prof. Ahmed El Shamsy (UChicago NELC)</li>
<li>5/04 – Developing the Hafsa Archive: Evaluating the History and Continuity of Palestinian Oral Tradition w/ Marah Abdel Jaber (UChicago CMES MA)</li>
<li>5/11 – The Banū Hilāl Myth and Statecraft in the Maghrib w/ Sabrina Amrane (UChicago CMES MA)</li>
<li>5/18 – Teaching the Ottoman ‘Middle Period(s)’: Historiographic, Methodological, and Pedagogical Challenges w/ Arlen Wiesenthal (UChicago NELC)</li>
<li>5/25 – The Lives and Journeys of a Sufi in Ottoman and Mamluk Lands w/ Dr. Mustafa Kaya (UChicago CMES Preceptor)</li>
<li>5/26 – Lunch Discussion of the "Sultan's Syllabus" Debate w/ Prof. Tunç Şen (Columbia University)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MEHAT" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thank you to all participants and presenters for an excellent year of MEHAT gatherings. Here is a brief overview of our events during the past year:]]></summary></entry></feed>